Guide to the Stokely Carmichael-Lorna D. Smith collection, 1964-1972
Department of Special Collections
Stokely Carmichael-Lorna D. Smith collection,
1964-1972
Special Collections M0170
Carmichael, Stokely.
5 linear ft.
Stanford University. Libraries. Dept. of Special Collections and University Archives.
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
None.
Provenance
Gift of Lorna D. Smith, donated as collected, beginning in 1966.
Scope and Content
This collection consists of correspondence, an inscribed book, and 15 scrapbooks filled with clippings from newspapers, magazines, circulars, folders, conference advertisements, and programs dating from July, 1964 to Nov. 1972. All of the items relate directly to Stokely Carmichael and to his work with the Student Nonviolent Coordinating Committee, and to his role in the Black Power movement, racial unrest, rioting in American cities (as represented by the Press).
The correspondence is mostly addressed to Mrs. Lorna Smith in reference to her work on the Mississippi Summer Project of 1964 or her later help with the efforts of SNCC, including 55 letters from Carmichael dating from December, 1964 to Nov. 1972. These are fairly personal in nature.
Included in the collection is Freedom Summer, inscribed by the author Sally Belfrage. Some of her letters to Mrs. Smith are also found in the collection, relating her opinions of the representation Carmichael received in the press.
Additions received on: Dec., 1967 - Seventh scrapbook, clips dating from
Aug. to Nov. 1967.
Mar. 1968 - Eighth scrapbook, clips dating Nov. 67 to
Feb. 1968.
Apr. 30, 68 - Ninth scrapbook, clips dating Feb. 68 to Apr. 68
Aug. 1968 - Tenth scrapbook.
Jan. 2, 1969 - Eleventh scrapbook.
July 7, 1970 - Twelfth scrapbook.
Nov. 1970 - 2 letters to Mrs. Smith, 7-8-70 from Carmichael, and 7-12-68 from Ukita.
SEE DONOR CARD FILE FOR FURTHER ADDITIONS.
Biographical Note
1941 born in Trinidad
1952 family moved to Harlem, New York and later to the East Bronx
1960 graduated from the Bronx High School of Science
1964 graduated from Howard University with a B.A. in Philosophy
1964 field secretary of Student Nonviolent Coordinating Committee
1966 May elected chairman of SNCC
Container List
- Scrapbooks
  - clippings dating from July 1964 through July 1966.taken from all major newspapers and magazines as well as the following: The Salt Lake Tribune, Nat'l Guardian, Movement, Southern Courier, New Republic, I. F. Stone's Weekly, Memphis Press Scimitar, Commercial Appeal, Jackson Daily News, Jet (Box 1, Volume I)
    also envelopes from Carmichael, photo of marcher (June, 1966), circular letters, receipts
  - clippings dating from July 1966 through August 1966.These are taken from a similar assortment of newspapers and magazines as well as: Kansas City Star, Christian Science Monitor, Harpers, CORE-LATOR, publications by the Santa Clara Valley Chapter Congress of Racial Equality. (Box 1, Volume II)
    Included are assorted items similar to those described above
  - clippings dating from August 1966 through October.Additional sources: Commonweal, Mid-Valley News, Ebony, Village Voice, Liberation, New Student, Young Socialist, Los Angeles Free Press Sunday Ramparts, Fellowship. assorted ephemera (Box 2, Volume III)
  - clippings dating from October 1966 through January 1967.Additional sources: A Radical Newspaper, Atlanta Black Paper (an abridgement printed in The Movement), Muhammed Speaks, The Progressive, The Independent Socialist. ephemera (Box 2, Volume IV)
  - clippings dating from February 1967 through March 1967.Additional sources: Spartan Daily, The Greensboro Daily News, Social Questions Dulletin, Together, News Notes (Central Comm. C.O.s), The Listener, Counterpart. assorted ephemera (Box 3, Volume V)
  - clippings dating from April 1967 through August 1967.Additional sources: Fact, New Politics, Four Lights, League for Industrial Democracy, assorted ephemera. (Box 3, Volume VI)
  - clippings dating Aug. 1967-Nov. 1967 (Box 5, Volume VII)
  - clippings dating Nov. 1967-Feb. 1968 (Box 5, Volume VIII)
  - clippings dating Feb. 1968-Apr. 1968 (Box 6, Volume IX)
  - clippings dating Apr. 1968-July 1968 (Box 6, Volume X)
  - clippings dating July 1968-Dec. 1968 (Box 7, Volume XI)
  - clippings dating Jan.1969 -Dec.1969;including Mrs. Smith's certificate of membership in the D. A. R. (Box 7, Volume XII)
  - 1968, Jan. 1970-Dec. 1970.Invasion of Guinea by Portugal. (Box 7, Volume XIII)
  - clippings dating July 1969; 1970; Jan. 1971-Dec. 1971; Jan. -Feb. 1972. (Box 8, Volume XIV)
  - clippings dating March 1972-Nov. 1972. (Box 8, Volume XV)
  - clippings dating December 1972-October 1973. (Box 8, Volume XVI)
  - clippings 1973 [UNK], 1 Folder
- CORRESPONDENCE OF STOKELY CARMICHAEL (Box 4, Folder 1)
  - 1965, Dec. 23to Mrs. Lorna Smith, T.L.S.
  - 1965, Dec. 31to Mrs. Lorna Smith, T.L.
  - 1966, Jan. 12to Mrs. Lorna Smith, T.L.S.
  - 1966, Jan. 15to Mrs. Lorna Smith, A.L.S.
  - 1966, Feb. 10to Mrs. Lorna Smith, A.L.S.
  - 1966, Mar. 4to Mrs. Lorna Smith, A.L.S.
  - 1966, Mar. 21to Mrs. Lorna Smith, A.L.S.
  - 1966, Mar. 29to Mrs. Lorna Smith, A.L.S.
  - 1966, Mar. 31to Mrs. Lorna Smith, T.L.
  - 1966, Apr. 15to Mrs. Lorna Smith, T.L.S.
  - 1966, May 18to Mrs. Douglas Matthews, T.L.S.
  - 1966, June 15T. L. to Mrs. Lorna Smith
  - 1966, June 22T. L. to Mrs. Lorna Smith
  - 1966, Aug. 3to Mrs. Lorna Smith, T.L.S.
  - 1966, Aug. 20to Mrs. Lorna Smith, T.L.
  - 1966, Aug. 23to Mrs. Lorna Smith, T.L.
  - 1966, Sept. 1to Mrs. Lorna Smith Gift of Mrs. Mary Carter, T.L.
  - 1966, Nov. 19Tape recording of S. Carmichael at Santa Clara Valley Friends of SNCC meeting.
  - 1967, Jan. 11to Mrs. Lorna Smith, T.L.
  - 1967, Jan. 28to Mrs. Lorna Smith, T.L.
  - 1967, Feb. 4to Mrs. Lorna Smith, T.L.
  - 1967, Feb. 13to Mrs. Lorna Smith, T.L.
  - 1967, Mar. 14to Mrs. Lorna Smith, T.L.
  - 1967, May 2to Mrs. Lorna Smith, T.L.
  - 1967, June 2to Mrs. Lorna Smith, T.L.
  - 1967, July 12to Mrs. Lorna Smith, T.L.
  - 1968, Jan. 23to Mrs. Lorna Smith, T.L.S.
  - 1968, Jan. 30to Mrs. Lorna Smith, T.L.
  - 1968, May 9to Mrs. Lorna Smith, T.L.
  - 1968, May 27to Mrs. Lorna Smith, T.L.
  - 1968, June 18to Mrs. Lorna Smith, T.L.
  - 1968, Oct. 26to Mrs. Lorna Smith, T.L.
  - 1970, Feb. 23to Mrs. Lorna Smith, T.L.S.
  - 1970, May 25to Mrs. Lorna Smith, T.L.S.
  - 1970, July 14to Mrs. Lorna Smith, A.L.S.
  - 1970, Aug. 7to Mrs. Lorna Smith, A.L.S.
  - 1970, Oct. 6to Mrs. Lorna Smith, A.L.S.
  - 1970, Nov. 2to Mrs. Lorna Smith, T.L.S. & clip
  - 1970, Dec. 9to Mrs. Lorna Smith, T.L.S.
  - 1970, Dec. 26to Mrs. Lorna Smith, T.L.S.
  - 1971, Feb. 5to Mrs. Lorna Smith, P.C.S. & xerox
  - 1971, June 14to Mrs. Lorna Smith, P.C.S. & xerox
  - 1971, Aug. 15to Mrs. Lorna Smith, T.L.S.
  - 1971, Sept. 24Mrs. Lorna Smith, T.L.S. & clip
  - 1971, Oct. 17to Mrs. Lorna Smith, T.L.S.
  - 1971, Dec. 6to Mrs. Lorna Smith, T.L.S.
  - 1972, Mar. 19to Mrs. Lorna Smith, T.L.S.
  - 1972, Apr. 18to Mrs. Lorna Smith, T.L.S.
  - 1972, May. 23to Mrs. Lorna Smith, T.L.S.
  - 1972, June 16to Mrs. Lorna Smith, T.L.S.
  - 1972, July 23to Mrs. Lorna Smith, T.L.S.
  - 1972, Aug. 9by L.S. to P. Palmer, T.L.S. & note
  - 1972, Aug. 29to P. Palmer, T.L.S.
  - [1972?]to P. Palmer, P.C.S.
  - [1972?]to P. Palmer, P.C.S.
  - Nov. 28to P. Palmer, T.L.S.
  - 1913, July 24to Mrs. Lorna Smith, A.L.S.
    (Xerox copy included).
  - 1976[UNK] to L.S., Xerox of ALS
  - 1977, June 20to L.S., A.L.S.
  - 1977, Aug. 20to L.S., ALS
- GENERAL CORRESPONDENCE (Box 4, Folder 2)
  - 1964, Oct. 30from Mrs. Eliz. G. Kirschten to Mrs. Lorna Smith, T.L.S.
  - 1964, Nov. 10from Mrs. Eliz. G. Kirschten to Mrs. Lorna Smith, T.L.S.
  - 1966, Jan. 6from J. Benton White to Mrs. Lorna Smith, T.L.S.
  - 1966, June 6from Mattie Pilcher to Mrs. Lorna Smith, A.L.S.
  - 1966, July 19from J. Benton White to Mrs. Lorna Smith, T.L.S.
  - 1966, July 25from Cathy Archibald to Mrs. Lorna Smith, T.L.S.
  - 1966, July 29from Rico Holman to Mrs. Smith, A.L.S.
  - 1966, Aug. 23from Nicholas George to Mrs. Smith, T.L.S.
  - 1966, Aug. 26from Dwight Newton to Mrs. Smith, A.L.S.
  - 1966, Sept. 17from Ryo Namkiawa to Mrs. Smith, A.L.S.
  - [1966, Aug.?]from Ryo Namkiawa to Mrs. Smith, A.L.S.
  - [no date]from Gladys [?] to Mrs. Smith, A.L.S.
  - 1966, Nov. 3Ryo Namkiawa to L.S. re: translation (Japanese) of Freedom Summer, A.L.S.
  - 1966, Dec. 3Ryo Namkiawa to L.S. re: translation (Japanese) of Freedom Summer, A.L.S.
  - 1967, Mar. 17Ryo Namkiawa to L.S. re: translation (Japanese) of Freedom Summer, A.L.S.
  - [1967, Mar. 29?]Ryo Namkiawa to L.S. re: translation (Japanese) of Freedom Summer, A.L.S.
  - 1967, Apr. 14Ryo Namkiawa to L.S. re: translation (Japanese) of Freedom Summer, A.L.S.
  - 1967, Aug. 24Hisako to L. S. [Ukita], A.L.S.
  - 1968, Feb. 13to Jeannette, T.L.S.
  - 1968, May 4Hisako to L. S., T.L.S.
  - 1968, May 6Robert D. Horn to L.S., T.L.S.
  - 1968, June 9Edith M. to L.S., T.L.S.
  - 1968, June 12L.S. to Stokely Carmichael
  - 1968, Aug. 28Koko to L.S., A.L.S.
  - 1968, Dec. 7Hisako to L.S., T.L.S.
  - 1969, Jan. 26KoKo to L.S., P.C.S.
  - 1970, Oct. 10photostat of Stokely [UNK] to [UNK] [UNK]., T.L.S.
  - 1971, July 26Charlotte [KRETZOI] to L.S., T.L.S. (xerox)
  - 1972, Nov. 3Jan Bailey to L.S., T.L.S.
  - 1974.MIRIAM MAKEBA to L.S., ALS. 2 [UNK]
  - [1974].Charlotle [KRETZOI] to L.S., Postcard (two)
  - 1974, April 6.Bill & mary Carter to L.S., ALS.
  - 1974, Mar. 4.Bill & mary Carter to L.S., ALS.
  - Commencement announcement - San Jose State College - William Carter, Aug. 28, 1970., Photo of Wm. Carter
  - 1974, March 30.Bill & mary Carter to [UNK] one greeting card to LDS from the Carters, ANS.
  - 1974, Sept. 30[UNK] B.[UNK] to L.S., ALS
  - 1976, June 29[UNK] HUNT to L.S. [UNK] [UNK], ALS
    - a) Program - African Liberation Day
      - -National Black Leadership [UNK]
    - b) News Releases: AAPRP
  - Freedom Summer, by Sally Belfrage, 1965Viking Press. Book is inscribed by the author to honor two fighters for freedom, Stokely Carmichael and Lorna Smith.
    - Tape 1 - Mrs. Carter (gift of)
    - Tape 2 - Interview with Lorna Smith (Aug. 1967)
    - Tape 3 - David Frost Show, interview with S. C.
- CORRESPONDENCE - SALLY BELFRAGE TO LORNA SMITH (Box 4, Folder 3)
  - 1963, July 16S.B. to L.S. re: her father leaving Cuba, now in Mexico., T.L.S.
  - [1964], Oct. 2S.B. to L.S. re: the book, [ Freedom Summer], A.L.S.
  - [1965], June 13S.B. to L.S. re: book., A.L.S.
  - [1965, Aug. 5?]S.B. to L.S. re: thanks for letter to San Francisco Chronicle, A.L.S.
  - [1965, Aug. 13?]S.B. to L.S. re: namesin the book., A.L.S.
  - [1965, Sept.2?]S.B. to L.S. re: a book review., A.N.S.
  - [1965, Sept.23?]S.B. to L.S. re: a book review, plans for a visit., A.L.S.
  - [1965, Oct. 14]S.B. to L.S. re: meeting in N.Y., A.L.S.
  - 1965, Nov. 17S.B. to L.S. re: she's marrying., A.L.S.
  - 1966, Jan. 6Sally Belfrage Pomerance to L.S. re: Nick's book., A.L.S.
  - 1966, Mar. 5,S.B.P. to L.S. re: Freedom Summer voted one of 25 best books for young people, A.L.S.
  - [1966] Mar. 19,S.B.P. to L.S. re: a quote about Mrs. Smith, A.N.S.
  - [1966] Apr. 30,S.B.P. to L.S. re: SNCC bldg. burned down & the Freedom Information Service, A.L.S.
  - 1966, June 19from Sally [Belfrage Pomerance] to Mrs. Lorna Smith, A.L.S.
  - [1966, June 29?],S.B.P. to L.S., A.N.S.
  - [1966] July 21,S.B.P. to L.S., A.N.S.
  - [1966, July 29],S.B.P., to L.S., A.N.S.
  - 1966, Aug 3,S.B.P. to L.S. re: Willie James trouble with distribution, T.L.S.
  - [1966, Aug. 10?],S.B.P. to L.S., A.N.S.
  - 1966, oct. 8,S.B.P. to L.S. re: L.S. in Time, Emma Gelders Sterne's book about Rose Parks, research about Rose Parks, Prof. Namikawa, T.L.S.
  - 1966, Oct. 15,S.B.P. to L.S. re: difficulty in contacting Mrs. Parks, T.L.S.
  - [1966, Oct. 20?],S.B.P. to L.S. re: Vikings arrangements for Japanese translation of Freedom Summer, contact with Mrs. Parks, A.L.S.
  - [1966, Oct. 24?],S.B.P. to L.S., A.N.S.
  - [1966] Oct. 24,S.B.P. to L.S. re: baby coming, Stokely's Susskind program, A.L.S.
  - [1966] Oct. 27,S.B.P. to L.S. re: Stokely at Berkeley, A.L.S.
  - [1966, Oct.?]from Sally [Belfrage Pomerance] to Mrs. Smith, A.L.S.
  - [1966, Nov. 11?],S.B.P. to L.S. re: Sussking show which was rescheduled., A.N.S.
  - [1966, Nov. 14?],S.B.P. to L.S., A.N.S.
  - [1966, Nov. 22?],S.B.P. to L.S., A.N.S.
  - [1966] Dec. 13,S.B.P. to L.S. re: her work on R. Peter Straus, the Carters (friends of Mrs. Parks), T.L.S.
  - [1966, Dec. 14?]T.N.S., S.B.P. to L.S.
  - 1966, Dec. 23,S.B.P, to L.S. re: Canadian edition, visiting the Carters, T.L.S.
  - [1966, Dec. 28?],S.B.P. to L.S. re: The Southern Patriot, A.N.S.
  - [1966, Dec. 31],S.B.P. to L.S. re: Job Corps, Crusader Without Violence (Martin Luther King), A Doctor for the People (Dr. Michael A. Shadid), A.N.S.
  - 1967, Feb. 13,S.B.P. to L.S., A.N.S.
  - 1967, Mar 14,S.B.P. to L.S. re: birth of baby girl, A.L.S.
  - 1967, Apr. 18,S.B.P. to L.S. re: Carmichael, A.L.S.
  - [1967], May 22S.B.P. to L.S. re: John Gunther, A.L.S.
  - 1967, June 20S.B.P. to L.S. re: third world, A.N.S.
  - 1967, July 29S.B.P. to L.S. re: Communist Party, F.B.I., S.D.S., and Carmichael, T.L.S.
  - [1967, Sept.?]S.B.P. to L.S., A.N.S.
  - [1968, Apr. 12?]S.B.P. to L.S. re: moving to London, A.N.S.
  - [1967? Oct. 31[?] to L. S. from a member of Sally's family., A.N.S.
  - 1967, Sept. 1to Mary, Bill and Lorna, T.L.S.
  - [1968] June 5to Lorna, A.L.S.
  - [1968] June 27to Lorna, A.L.S.
  - 1968 Aug. 19to Lorna, A.L.S.
  - 1968 Feb. The Haunted House of Ernest Hemingway by Sally Belfrage. Esquire, Feb. pp. 66-7.
- Two sets of bibliography cards re: books mentioning Stokely Carmichael. (Box 4, Folder 4)
- Bibliography of Stokely Carmichael. (Box 4, Folder 5.)
- Magazines: 1. Black Collegian, 1976, Jan-Feb. (Box 4, Folder 6.)
- 2. Race Today, 1974, Nov.
- Stokely Carmichael on David Frost show, 4/20/70, and n.d., 2 tapes, reel to reel. (Box 4, Folder 7.)
- Scrapbook of newspaper and magazine clippings. Aug. 1967 to Nov. 1967. (Box 5.)
- Scrapbook of newspaper and magazine clippings. Nov. 1967 - Mar. 1968. (Box 6.)
- Scrapbook of newspaper and magazine clippings. Feb. 1968 - May 1968. (Box 7.)
- Scrapbook of newspaper and magazine clippings. May 1968 - July 1968. (Box 8.)
- Scrapbook of newspaper and magazine clippings. July 1968 - Jan 1969. (Box 9.)
- Scrapbook of newspaper and magazine clippings. Jan 1969 - Dec 1969. (Box 10.)
- Scrapbook of newspaper and magazine clippings. Jan 1970- Dec 1970.
- Scrapbook of newspaper and magazine clippings. Jan 1972 - Jul 1972,plus miscellaneous articles and photographs. (Box 11.)
- Scrapbook of newspaper and magazine clippings. Oct 1972 - Nov 1973.
- Miscellaneous loose clippings, 1973 - (Box 11., Folder 1.)
- A Negro in the state of Washington, 1788-1967, a biography compiled by the Washington State Library, Jan., 1968.
- Stokely Carmichael (material to, from, and about him) (Box 12., Folder 1.)
  - July 26, 1978.Sylvia (?) to Lorna Smith, ANS.
  - May 23, 1971.Miriam Makeba to Lorna Smith., TLS.
  - Apr. 18, 1972.S.C. to L.S., TLS xerox.
  - May 24, 1978.Bisi Payne to L.S. (cc S.C.), TLS.
  - Jun 7, 1978.Bisi Payne to L.S. (cc S.C.), TLS.
  - Jul 22, 1978.S.C. to L.S., TLS.
  - Dec 14, 1978.S.C. to L.S., TLS.
  - May 28, 1979.Jeanne (?) to L.S., ALS.
- Miscellaneous clippings of Carmichael: n.d., 4 clippings, one in Chinese (Box 12., Folder 2.)
  - Stokely: Civilization and mind over matter, from The Campus Digest, Tuskeegee Inst., Nov 7, 75.
  - Brief Biographical Chart of Carmichael, May 21, 1975.
  - Carmichael refutes Zionists' Claim, American University, Washington, D.C., Nov 17, 1975.
  - Brittanica Library Research Service, booklet of several articles and comments on S.C.
- Born Black by Gordon Parks, a personal report on the decade of black revolt, 1960-70.(One chapter devoted to Carmichael). (Box 12., Folder 3.)